Guide to the Buckingham Smith papers and collected materials, 1529-1941, n.d. MS 2413
New-York Historical Society
Buckingham Smith papers and collected materials
1529-1941, n.d.
New-York Historical Society
Smith, Buckingham, 1810-1871
MS 2413
6 Linear feet
The collection documents Smith's extensive research on the Spanish colonization of North America. The bulk of the collection consists of Smith's own notes and correspondence, in addition to his collection of manuscripts and maps, mostly related to the history of Florida. Topics discussed in the correspondence include Smith's acquisition of manuscripts and rare books; his service as a diplomat in Mexico and Spain; and the history of St. Augustine, Florida. The collection includes original documents and transcriptions of the Timucuan language; dictionaries of Native American languages; and correspondence from Spanish Catholic missionaries about Native Americans. Map of the coast of Florida from BV2 is digitized and available in the Shelby White and Leon Levy Digital Library.
Related Materials Note
Information concerning the the acquisition of Smith's books, archival collections and art objects by N-YHS can be found in: New-York Historical Society Institutional Archive management committee records (NYHS-RG 1), Series IV. Official Papers, Folder: Official Papers. 1872 (6 of 6). Buckingham Smith Acquisition.
Additional items related to Smith within the New-York Historical Society Institutional Archive can be found in: General Correspondence (NYHS-RG 2), folder label: Correspondence. 1858 January-April and General Correspondence (NYHS-RG 2), folder label: 1927-29 Correspondence. R (3 of 3).
Published books, either owned or authored by Smith, can be located in the online catalog by searching the term "Buckingham Smith."
Scope and Contents Note
The bulk of the collection consists of Smith's own notes and correspondence, in addition to his collection of manuscripts and maps, mostly related to the history of Florida.
Topics discussed in Smith's correspondence include the acquisition of manuscripts and rare books; his service as a diplomat in Mexico and Spain; and the history of St. Augustine, Florida. Correspondents include Joseph Henry, scientist and secretary of the Smithsonian Institution; George Henry Moore, historian and librarian at N-YHS; and Francis Parkman, Jr., historian and trustee of the Boston Athenæum.
Smith's interest in Spanish colonization and Native American history is found throughout the collection. The collection includes original documents and transcriptions of the Timucuan language; dictionaries of Native American languages; and correspondence from Spanish Catholic missionaries about Native Americans. In addition, the collection includes hand-drawn replications of 17th-18th century maps of Florida and Mexico. Evidence of slavery and the slave trade can be found in correspondence from the mercantile firm Panton, Leslie & Company, and the "The Story of Uncle Jack," which is an account of one of Smith's slaves.
Biographical Note
Thomas Buckingham Smith was a lawyer, diplomat, antiquarian, and author. Smith was born on October 21, 1810 on Cumberland Island, Georgia. The family moved to St. Augustine, Florida in 1820, when Smith's father was appointed U.S. Consul to Mexico. Smith attended Trinity College in Hartford, Connecticut and earned a degree from Harvard Law School in 1836. Following graduation, Smith worked in the Maine office of Samuel Fessenden, a politician and abolitionist. He returned to St. Augustine in 1839 and served as a secretary to Robert R. Reid, governor of the Territory of Florida from 1839-1841. Smith served as a member of the Florida Territorial Legislative Council in 1841. He married Julia Gardner of Concord, New Hampshire in 1843.
Throughout his life, Smith was a devoted student of North American history, specifically Spanish colonialism and Native American cultures and languages. In order to further his studies, Smith lobbied U.S. government officials for diplomatic appointments abroad. He was successful in obtaining positions in the U.S. embassies of Mexico (1850-1852) and Spain (1855-1858). While abroad, Smith actively purchased, transcribed and translated manuscripts related to the Spanish colonization of North America. Smith also supplemented his income by selling rare books and manuscripts to collectors in the U.S., including Peter Force, an editor and politician, whose collection was purchased by the Library of Congress in 1867. During the 1850-1860s, Smith translated and edited several publications, including Colección de varios documentos para la historia de la Florida y tierras adyacentes (1857), A grammatical sketch of the Heve language (1861), Narratives of the career of Hernando de Soto in the conquest of Florida (1866), and Relation of Alvar Nunez Cabeca de Vaca (1871).
Smith died in New York City in 1871 and was buried in St. Augustine.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials in this collection may be stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Mexico -- History.; Florida -- History.; Timucua Indians; North America -- History -- Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775.; North America -- Discovery and exploration.; Slavery -- United States.; Slave traders -- United States.; Indians Of North America -- Languages -- Texts.; Indians Of North America; Núñez Cabeza de Vaca, Alvar, active 16th century; Schoolcraft, Henry Rowe, 1793-1864; Webster, Daniel, 1782-1852.; Moore, George Henry, 1823-1892; Hernandez, Joseph M. (Joseph Marion), 1788-1857; Parkman, Francis, Jr., 1823-1893; Henry, Joseph, 1791-1878; Force, Peter, 1790-1868; Fillmore, Millard, 1800-1874
- I. Personal papers, 1840-1941, n.d.
  Scope and Contents Note
  This series includes Smith's personal and professional correspondence; passports from Smith's travels in Europe; and a brief biography of Smith.
  - Correspondence, 1840-1870, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Related Archival Materials Note
    Additional correspondence can be found in bound volumes within Series II: Transcriptions and edited works.
    Includes personal and professional correspondence to and from Smith.
  - Legal and financial documents, 1850 November 26, circa 1861-1870 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Includes a summons from the Court of the Confederate States in 1862 and a tax bill from St. John's County, Florida in 1870.
  - Letter book, 1851-1852 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Includes copies of Smith's correspondence written while employed at the U.S. embassy of Mexico. Smith discusses of the affairs of the delegation; impressions of Mexican political officials; the sale of books and manuscripts; and personal expenses. Includes correspondence to Millard Fillmore, Daniel Webster, Henry R. Schoolcraft. Also contains Spanish language transcriptions of manuscripts related to the colonization of Mexico.
  - Passports, 1858, 1868 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Includes two passports with stamps from Spain and Portugal.
  - Clippings and ephemera, circa 1860s (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Includes clippings in Spanish and English, in addition to calling cards from Ms. Buckingham Smith.
  - Notebook and scrapbook, circa 1840s-1860s (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Notebook includes names and addresses of New York residents. Scrapbook contains printed clippings of poems.
  - Memorials and archive survey, 1901, 1941, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Includes photocopies of an N-YHS Quarterly Bulletin and text of a speech related to a tablet unveiling for Smith in St. Augustine. Also includes a photocopied survey of the Smith papers and collected materials created by the Alabama Historical Society.
- II. Transcriptions and edited works, 1835-1871, n.d.
  This series includes transcriptions, mostly created by Smith and made from documents held in archives in Spain and England. The documents are primarily related to the history of North American colonization and Native American languages. Also included are drafts of The Story of Uncle Jack, a first-person narrative about Sitiki, or "Uncle Jack," an African-American slave, who was owned by Smith's family.
  - "Don Manuel de Montiano", 1835 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Includes transcriptions of correspondence and documents from Don Manuel de Montiano, governor of East Florida from 1737-1741.
  - "For a History of the Discover, Invasions and Settlement of Florida", circa 1840s-1860s (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Includes an index of manuscripts, published works, and maps from the 16th-19th centuries related to the history of Florida.
  - "The Recapture of Florida by Captain Gourges", circa 1850s (Box 1, Folder 10)
    A bound volume of transcriptions about Dominique de Gourgue, 1530–1593, a French soldier, who attacked the Spanish in Florida. Transcription possibly made at the National Library of Spain in Madrid.
  - "Letters to the Captain General of Cuba", circa 1850-1856 (Volume BV 1)
    A bound volume and folder of transcriptions, primarily correspondence, from the governors of Cuba and Florida, circa 1737-1741.
  - Transcriptions and correspondence, circa 1853 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    A bound volume of transcriptions of 16th century documents related to the Spanish colonization of Florida and the Americas. Also contains correspondence to Smith.
  - Transcriptions, correspondence and maps, 1854-1858 (Volume BV 2)
    A bound volume of transcriptions of 17th-18th century documents. Originals likely reside at the Royal Academy of History in Madrid, Spain. Also includes hand-drawn maps and correspondence to Smith.
    Existence and Location of Copies
    Digital copy of map removed from volume available in the Shelby White and Leon Levy Digital Library.
  - Transcriptions, circa 1855-1858 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    A bound volume of transcriptions of 16th-18th century documents related to the Spanish colonization of the Americas. Originals likely reside at the British Museum and the General Archive of Simancas in Spain.
    Access Restrictions
    Available on Buckingham Smith Mircrofilm.
  - "North American Transcripts 1500-60", circa 1855-1856 (Volume BV 8)
    Available on Buckingham Smith Microfilm.
    A bound volume of transcriptions and hand-drawn maps related to Spanish colonization of North America. Originals likely reside at various archives in Madrid.
  - "North American Transcripts 1561-93", circa 1856-1857 (Volume BV 9)
    A bound volume of transcriptions related to Spanish colonization of North America. Includes tracing of Ponce de Leon's crest. Originals likely reside at various archives in Madrid.
  - "Algunos reparos sobre la Historia, o' Noticia de la California", 1857 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    A bound volume of transcriptions related to the history of California made "from the original papers in the Royal Library [Academy?] of History" in Madrid, Spain.
  - "Coleccion de varios documentos para la historia de la Florida y tierras adyacentes...", 1857 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Includes a hand-written "prospectus" and excerpted copy of Smith's publication about the history of Florida.
  - "Condition of the Indians at Cape Florida in the year 1743 described by two Catholic missionaries at the Order of Jesus.", 1858 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Includes a translation of an 1743 document from the Royal Academy of History in Madrid, Spain.
  - "Florida Transcripts 1526-1743", circa 1860s (Volume BV 7)
    A bound volume of transcriptions related to Spanish colonization of Florida.
  - Transcriptions, correspondence and maps, circa 1868 (Volume BV 3)
    Available on Buckingham Smith Mircrofilm Reel 3.
    A bound volume of transcriptions of 16th century documents. Originals likely reside at the General Archive of Simancas. Also contains correspondence to Smith and hand-drawn maps.
  - "Relation of Alvar Nunez Cabeca de Vaca", circa 1871 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Includes proof copies of Relation with Smith's hand-written notes.
  - Eudeva transcriptions and translations (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Includes transcriptions of "Cartilla Eudeva" and "Arte y Vocabulario de La Lengua Dohema, Heve o Eudeva."
  - Narrative of Alvar Nunez Cabeca de Vaca, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Includes chapters of Narrative and Smith's notes.
  - Notes and translations (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Includes Smith's notes on the Timucuan language, his edition of "Relation of Alvar Nunez Cabeca de Vaca," and other research projects.
  - "The Story of Uncle Jack", n.d. (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Related Materials Note
    Smith's drafts were published in The Odyssey of an African Slave by Sitiki and edited by Patricia C. Griffin, published by the University Press of Florida in 2009.
    Includes drafts of The Story of Uncle Jack, a first-person narrative about Sitiki, or "Uncle Jack," an African-American slave, who was owned by Smith's family. Smith allegedly wrote the narrative in collaboration with Sitiki.
  - Unidentified transcriptions, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Includes two documents; one sent to a "Monsieur Pierre Paradis."
  - "Letter of Guzman", n.d. (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Includes Smith's notes and translation of "Letter of Guzman."
  - "Vida y hechos de Pedro Menéndez de Avilés, caballero de la Orden de Santiago, Adelantado de La Florida..." (Volume BV 4)
    Available on Buckingham Smith Mircrofilm Reel 1.
    A bound volume of transcriptions.
- III. Manuscripts, 1529[?]-1861, n.d.
  This series includes manuscripts collected by Smith. The manuscripts include documents and correspondence related to Catholic missionary work in Florida; documents and translations of Native American languages; and correspondence sent to John Leslie, co-founder of Panton, Leslie & Company, a mercantile firm involved in the slave trade.
  - Correspondence and reports, 1529[?]-1852, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 3)
    Includes manuscripts related to the Spanish colonization and Catholic missionary work in the Americas. Includes a 1676 list of convents in Florida and a 1726-1727[?] report from Joseph Escudero, a Franciscan friar.
  - Testimony of Luis de Huerta, 1578 June 7 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    Includes the testimony of Luis de Huerta, a notary public, in a petition by Alvar Nunez Cabeca de Vaca. Obtained by Smith in Seville on 1859 June 26. Possibly from the collection of Friar Juan Fogueras, a Spanish missionary.
  - "La prodigiosa navegacion de la Nave Santa Elena, que venia de la India de Portugal...", 1613, 1735 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    Physical Characteristics Note
    Bound in a folder stamped, "Spain Legation of the United States of America." Found in a parchment portfolio dated 1735.
    Includes a report about a ship, the Santa Elena, and a parchment folder.
  - Timucua and Apalache documents, 1688, 1866, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 6)
    Available on Buckingham Smith Microfilm Reel 3.
    Includes manuscripts written in Timucua, Apalache, and Spanish, in addition to a disbound volume with printed Spanish translations. Inscription on volume reads, "The New-York Historical Society, these copies in seven sheets of original Spanish documents in the Timuguana and Apalache languages of Florida, from Buckingham Smith. October 2, 1866."
  - "Compendio histórico de los descubrimientos conquistas y establecimientos del Nuevo-Mundo", 1781 (Volume BV 5)
    A bound manuscript regarding the "conquest and establishment of the New World" written by Bernardo de Estrada.
  - John Leslie correspondence, 1781-1811 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    Includes correspondence sent to John Leslie, co-founder of Panton, Leslie & Company, a mercantile firm in St. Augustine. Topics discussed include the sale of cattle and deerskins, conflicts with Native Americans, and the slave trade.
  - John Hambley diaries, 1794 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    Includes the daily diaries of John Hambly, a shopkeeper for Panton, Leslie and Company, and an interpreter of Native Americans languages.
  - Joseph Marion Hernández correspondence, 1815-1838, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 9)
    Includes correspondence to Joseph Marion Hernández, a plantation owner in Florida and brigadier general in the U.S. Army.
  - "Return of killed and wounded in the Battle of Withlacoochie", 1835 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    Includes list of troops and militia wounded or killed in the Battle of Withlacoochee [Ouithlacoochie] during the Second Seminole War.
  - Fairmont Bank dollar bills, 1861 July 13 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    Includes unsigned dollar bills. Inscription on verso: "One of many unsigned dollar bills taken from the military chest of General Garnett's army at the battle of Corrick's Ford, Cheat River, July 13, 1861, Bunham[?] Corps of Engineers Commanding."
  - "Arte de la Lengua Pima", n.d. (Box 4, Folder 2)
    A bound manuscript about the Pimo Bajo language.
  - "Arte y Vocabulario de La Lengua Dohema, Heve o Eudeva", n.d. (Box 4, Folder 3)
    A bound dictionary of the Eudeve language.
  - "Compendio del Idioma Mexicano Segun el metodo, y ensenanza del Son. D. Rafael de Sandoval..." (Box 4, Folder 4)
    Includes a dictionary of the "Mexican language according to the method and teachings of the Son. D. Rafael De Sanadoval..."
  - "Vocabulario en Lengua Nevome", n.d. (Volume BV 6)
    Available on Misc. Mss. Microfilm Reel 4
    A bound dictionary of the Nevome language.
- IV. Maps and visual materials, 1858, circa 1860s, n.d.
  This series primarily includes hand-drawn replications of maps of Florida, Mexico and California.
  - Map of Anastasia Island, 1858 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    A bound volume of hand-drawn replications of maps. Inscription on verso: "Half size of the original map in the Royal Deposit Hydrography at Madrid signed by Juan Elixio de la Puente 'Hav[?]a 16 de Febrero 1769'... Madrid: 12 August 1858 Buckingham Smith."
  - Maps of Florida, 1858 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    Available on Buckingham Smith Mircrofilm Reel 3
    A bound volume of hand-drawn replications of maps from the Hydrographic Deposit in Madrid, Spain.
  - Maps, circa 1860s, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 7)
    Includes printed and hand-drawn maps of Mexico, California and other areas of Spanish colonization.
  - Visual materials, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 8)
    Includes prints of Pedro Menendez de Aviles and an ink drawing of a Native American glyph.
- V. Published works, 1739-1864
  This series includes published works and chapbooks collected by Smith.
  - "Fray Juan de la Rosa, Procurador General de la Provincia de la Florida, en vuestros Reynos de las Indias.", 1739 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    Includes a publication from the office of Juan de la Rosa, Attorney General of the Province of Florida, concerning missionary work.
  - "Satisfacion que se da por el M.R.P. Fr. Juan Fogueras...", 1747 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    Includes a publication "about the established right to return declared in the election...held in the province of Santa Elena in Florida, the day 23 of January in the year 1745..."
  - Chapbooks, 1863-1864 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    Includes two chapbooks, Historia de Orlando Furioso and Historia verdadera del valiente Bernardo del Carpio.